AI imposes super weird constraints on your code base, and most code bases out there in the world
probably including yours are not ready. Your code base way more than the prompt that you used
way more than your agents.md file is the biggest influence on AI's output, and if it's designed
wrong, it can cost you in a bunch of different ways. It can mean that the AI doesn't receive feedback
fast enough, so it doesn't know if what it changed actually did what it intended. It can find it super
hard to make sense of things, and find files, and work out even how to test things. And finally,
it can lead you into cognitive burnout as you try to hold together AI and your code base and
patch it all up and keep everything in your mind. And my thesis here is that software quality matters
more than ever. In other words, how easy your code base is to change makes a huge impact on how
AI then goes and changes it, and the stuff that we've known about software best practices for 20 years
still holds more true than ever. And if you're interested in getting better at this stuff, then check
out my newsletter AI hero. I teach you all about AI coding, but this is not full vibe coders. This
is for real engineers solving real problems. And if that's you and you're not sure how to handle
these new tools, then you are going to love it. Now let's imagine that this here is our code base.
Each one of these little squares represents a module, and this module might export some functionality,
it might export a function, it might export some variables, it might export a component if it's like
a react or a frontend thing. I want you to imagine that this is the image of your code base that you
hold in your head. Now you might inside here have some vague groupings of different functionality. For
instance, here you might have let's say a thumbnail editor feature, and all of these different modules
contribute to that. Over here you might have a little video editor feature or something. Down here
is all the code related to authentication. Up here is a bunch of crud forms for updating stuff, maybe
in a CMS. And over here are a couple of example features that I can't be bothered to think of examples
for. Now this map that I've created here of all of the located modules, in this particular code base,
they're not actually reflected that much in the file system. They're all really jumbled up together.
If I want to just grab let's say an export from this module and import it down into this module,
I can. There's nothing stopping me. And so what you might end up with is a bunch of kind of disparate
relationships between stuff that doesn't actually relate to each other. Now you as the developer understand
the mental map between all of these modules. But what the AI sees when it first goes into your code base
is this. It doesn't see all of the natural groupings and all the natural relationships. What it
sees is a bunch of disparate modules that can all import from each other. That's because AI, when it
jumps into your code base, it has no memory. It has not experienced your code base before. It's like
the guy from the memento who just steps in and goes, okay, I'm here. Oh, what am I doing? So my first
assertion here is that you need to make sure that the file system and the design of your code base
matches this internal map that you have of it. This is because if you describe something over in
the video editor section and you use it via a prompt, then you want the AI to be able to find it
easily. The AI won't go in knowing every single function, every single module and what they're supposed
to do and how they link to each other. And the best way I have found to do that is with deep modules.
Now deep modules comes from this book here which is a philosophy of software design. And the idea is
that in order to make your system easily navigable and easy to change and also easy to test,
is that you have a deep module. So lots of implementation controlled by a simple interface.
What that looks like in terms of our graph is instead of many, many small modules, you end up with
these big chunks of modules with simple controllable interfaces. And this means that any exports from
these modules have to come from that interface. Now when I read that about deep modules, I immediately
thought about putting AI in control of these modules. Because this is an opportunity to introduce
a kind of seam into the co-base. I don't really care about what's happening inside here, which is
the implementation, I just care about what's happening in the interface. Because the interface,
which is, you know, the publicly accessible API of this module, I can carefully control and I can
apply my taste to and design. And then this stuff inside here, I can just delegate to an AI to control
and I can write tests that completely lock down the module in terms of its behavior. So these are
not just deep modules with simple interfaces, they're also gray box modules. In other words, I don't
actually need to look inside these modules. I can, if I want to, if I want to influence their outcome,
or if I need to apply some taste to the implementation or any to improve their performance or something,
but as long as the tests are good, then I don't really need to care about what happens inside. Now,
this has three massive benefits. The first one is that I can make my co-base way more navigable.
Let's, for the sake of argument, just call each of these services, right? The video editor service,
the thumbnail service, whatever. If I document these each inside their own folder and I have the
publicly accessible interface, kind of like really obvious in a type section, then the AI, when
it's exploring my co-base, it can see all of these different services on the file system. It can
read and understand the types that they export before it actually looks at the implementation.
And then it can say, okay, I've seen the interface. I understand what this does. I don't need to look
inside because I can just trust what it's returning. In other words, we've designed our co-base for
progressive disclosure of complexity. The interface sits at the top and it just explains what the module
does. And then when we need to, we can look inside the module and make changes to it or look at it to
understand its behavior more deeply. The second one is that we reduce the cognitive burnout of managing
this code base. Now, as a user, I can just go, right, I need something from, I don't know, this
made up feature, or let's say the authentication bit over here. Let's see what the public interface is.
Let's just grab that and use it. And instead of needing to think about the interrelationships between
all of these modules, I can just keep kind of like seven or eight lumps of stuff in my head and go,
okay, the AI manages the stuff inside that. I only need to worry about designing the interfaces and how
they fit together. Now, this, of course, is still a million miles away from vibe coding because you
need to apply taste at the boundaries of these modules. You need to be really good at deciding, okay,
what goes into that module, what goes into that module. And what you really want to avoid are lots
of little shallow modules, which is kind of what we had up here, right, each of these modules is just
like sure. It's kind of interrelated in group together, but really there are lots of tiny shallow modules,
which are testable in these tiny units, which are really hard to keep all in your head. And so by
simplifying the mental map of the code base, we reduce cognitive burnout that comes from managing
this code base. And again, this is nothing new. This is a 20-year-old software practice. And the third one
here, I mean, I'm really just repeating myself, but this is what we've been doing all along. This is
how good code bases have supposed to have been designed. So what works here for humans is also great
for AI. We need to stop thinking about AI as like this super-powered developer as like, you know, it's
going to reach AGI and understand that it's got some weird limitations. And the limitations that it
has are that it's a new starter in your code base. So you need to make your code base friendly and ready
for new starters, because you're going to be spawning like 20 new starters every day here, probably more
just to look at your code base and make changes. So that means the map of your code base needs to be
easily navigable and it needs to be enforced by using these modules. Now some languages make this
easier than others. For instance, in TypeScript and JavaScript, it's actually not that easy to make
these services, make these modules sort of boundary in this way. I want to give a quick shout-out to
effect, because I posted a video on effect a few months ago. I'm actually using effect way more than
I did back then. And it makes this kind of sort of seeming modularizing of your code base really
simple. The final thing I want to say here is that you need to be thinking about these modules and how
you're affecting them and how you're designing the interfaces in every coding session that you do.
That means right from the early planning stage, when you're writing your PRDs or when you're turning
your PRDs into implementation issues, you need to be thinking about the modules that you're
affecting and the interfaces and how you are going to test them. Because tests and feedback loops
are essential for an AI because of course, they're essential for a new starter joining the code base.
If you want a new starter to contribute effectively, you need a well-tested code base so they can see what
their changes do as they ripple out. So that's my rant for today. Your code base is probably not ready
for AI because you're not using enough deep modules. And instead you've got a web of interconnected
kind of shallow modules like this which are really hard to navigate and really hard to test and
really hard to keep in your head. Now if you dig this then of course you will dig my newsletter where
we go more deeply into topics like this. Thanks for watching folks, what else do you think goes into making
a great code base for AI? I really love this metaphor for deep modules but I know it's not the only one
going there are plenty out there. Thanks for watching and I will see you very soon. So when you're
thinking about your code base with AI, what are you thinking about? What kind of 20-year-old books do you
want to recommend? Leave it in the comments. It's the easiest way to keep up with all my stuff and the link
is below.